<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good mans priuiledge A sermon lately preached at Plimmouth in Deuon, by I.B. And now published at the request of some that then were auditors.</title>
            <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">959</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 959)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 695:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good mans priuiledge A sermon lately preached at Plimmouth in Deuon, by I.B. And now published at the request of some that then were auditors.</title>
                  <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 23, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by F[elix] K[ingston] for Nathaniel Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop, vnder St. Peters Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley, ouer against the signe of the white horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.B. = John Barlow.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:959:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:959:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOOD MANS PRIVILEDGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON LATELY PREACHED AT PLIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOVTH IN DEVON, By I. B. AND NOW PVBLISHED AT the requeſt of ſome that then were Auditors.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 4.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who will ſhew vs any good?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICAH. 6.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and in Popes-head Alley, ouer againſt the ſigne of the white horſe. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:959:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:959:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL FRANCIS DRAKE, OF BVCKLAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRAKE IN DEVON, Eſquire, <hi>I. B.</hi> wiſheth all grace and glory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am conſtrained (good Sir) to ſatisfie your deſire in ſo ſmall a requeſt, as the publiſhing of thoſe lines, whereunto ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you in your owne perſon gaue attention; and after the deliuery, an acceptable appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. Now if it be well done, you were the firſt mouer, and deſerue the honour of the action: but if not, I cannot impute the fault to any, except my ſelfe. Well; howeuer it be, I haue but done your deſire, and my owne duty: for I freely confeſſe, that your loue (many waies manifeſted to me) deſerues aboue my abilitie to make equall requital, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable ſatisfaction. You are well acquainted with my familiar phraſe, rude manner of ſpeaking; therefore I ceaſe to make any apology or defence in my owne behalfe: yet truth is truth, that as good
<pb facs="tcp:959:3"/> cloath may haue the courſeſt colour; the moſt precious ſtone bee put in the vncleaneſt corner, and ſometimes ſet too in the impureſt mettall: ſo may matter of great worth bee couched vnder a meane ſtile, and come to view in a familiar and plaine habit. For as the ſiluer veſſell, in which the meate is diſhed, doth not adde to the eſſence of the dyet, but comlineſſe and content: no more doe choiſe words to the truth deliuered; only they may giue ſome outward gloſſe which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and thats all.</p>
            <p>Might I ſpeake my opinion, then it is this: I doe affect and commend Rhetorique and elegancie of ſpeech with any, of any (for therein the wiſedome of God ſhineth): But to haue queint phraſe, and a neate ſtile amongſt the vulgar, is, though lawfull, not expedient. Hee therefore that will benefit the rude people, muſt ſpeake plainely, carry a low ſayle, and deſcend to their capacities. Was not our Lord Chriſt Wiſdome it ſelfe? did hee not notwithſtanding, draw ſimilitudes from the moſt familiar and common things; as the hiding of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the looſing of a groat, and children playing in the market place?</p>
            <p>Who wiſer (except the firſt and ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>) then <hi>Salomon?</hi> yet none plainer then hee in his Prouerbs: He telleth of wringing the noſe; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of milke; and of a ring in a Swines ſnout: was this want of art, wiſdome, or learning? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him that can and will (amongſt the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) grapple with his Greeke; flouriſh with his Fathers; bring foorth farre fetcht Etymologies,
<pb facs="tcp:959:3"/> and obſcure Hebraiſmes; but as for me, I either cannot, or will not. And thus I commend you, with all yours, vnto God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build further, and to giue you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all dutie: IOHN BARLOVV.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in Plymmouth,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 8. 1618.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:959:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:959:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, it is concluded (for our parts, whatſoeuer our aduerſaries affirme), that there are but two ends for all men at the laſt; either life, or death; ſaluation, or condemnation. Then from this truth I collect this neceſſary poſition; that, All men are either tending to the one, or trudging to the other. If thou bee in the narrow path (which is comfortable), theſe few lines will yeeld thee ſome (though little) roome, eaſe and ability, to goe on with the more cheerfulneſſe; the which to a wearie, and almoſt tyred traueller, cannot but giue good content: But, if thou be in the broad (which is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful), they may, through the good hand of God, be of force to cauſe thee ſmite thy hand vpon thy thigh, and alter thy iourney: For the producing of either which effects, was the cauſe I firſt preached it; and now ſince (though requeſted) haue penned it. Who knoweth not the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of mans will: how improne it is to run after the rule of Gods commands? And what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth that Good or Euill be the proper obiects for to moue and allure it to turne the perfect way? Then this being truth, reade theſe (though ragged) lines; for they will giue thee to ſee into many myſteries, ſecret things, that be in the courſe of godlineſſe; and declare vnto
<pb facs="tcp:959:5"/> thee, what thing is profitable for all things; ſo that, if thou canſt but obtaine one thing, thou ſhalt want nothing. Thou thinkeſt this a hard matter: Well, bee it ſo: yet reade on, and then conſider, conſult, and giue ſentence.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Ieſus,</hi> I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:959:5"/>
            <head>THE GOOD MANS PRIVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEDGE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And we know, that all things worke together for good, to them that loue God, and are called according to his purpoſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt many, three things haue, and doe moſt moleſt the children of God: One is, <hi>The guilt of ſinne;</hi> another, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred or originall corruption;</hi> the laſt is, <hi>troubles and affliction.</hi> Now the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, being a skilfull Phyſition, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth a threefold remedie for his diſtempered patients; the which being truly vnderſtood, and rightly applied, will expell the danger of the diſeaſes; and reſtore them that be ſicke thereof, vnto perfect ſoundneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt: Hee that would eſcape the guilt of his ſinnes, and be able to ſtand iuſt before God, muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon the merit of his owne workes; but by faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in, and reſt vpon Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> 
               <hi>For if the Lord ſhould marke what is done amiſſe, man were neuer able to abide it;</hi> neither the rigour of the Law, or the ſeuerity of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: But he that beleeueth in the Sonne of God, and is by faith made one with him, becommeth truly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.9.</note> ſo that <hi>the law of God cannot condemne him, or the iuſtice of God lay hold vpon him:</hi> for hee hath in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:959:6"/> Chriſt, and by him a righteouſneſſe, that can, and will giue a full payment, and an abſolute ſatisfaction, both to the Law, and the Author of it. Wherefore the Apoſtle maketh this peremptorie concluſion; that to ſuch <hi>There is no condemnation,</hi> verſ. 1. where by the way wee may learne a double leſſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, the vanity of the doctrine of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon their owne workes and worthineſſe for iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the Lord; when as <hi>Paul,</hi> though <hi>knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4.</note> yet confeſſeth ingeniouſly, <hi>hee was not thereby iuſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Againe, this muſt direct vs what to doe, when the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our ſinnes are too heauie for vs; <hi>viz.</hi> to labour <hi>to be found not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe,</hi> which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer anſwere the iuſtice of the law:<note place="margin">Phil. 3 9.</note> 
               <hi>but the righteouſneſſe which is by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For the ſecond; Inward and originall corruption will cauſe the man of God to droope, to hang downe the wing like a Hawke that is weather-beaten; and to cry out, <hi>Miſerable, or ſpoyled man that I am! who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> chap. 7.24. The remedie of this diſeaſe, is the powerfull operation of the Spirit, that deſtroyeth (by degrees) the curſed worke of Satan in vs; and perfecteth the good worke he hath begun within vs. Chap. 8. verſ. 11. whence we are taught,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, a reall difference betwixt him that is truly ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the man wholly in the ſtate of full corruption. For the one ſtriketh ſtill to cut,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.3.</note> and rend this euill tree vp at the roots; the other, onely to preuent and hinder the outward buds, and fruits that it produceth. Carnall men neuer looke to the fountaine from whence this bitter water ſpringeth, bubleth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And here we are inſtructed whither to runne for help, when we cannot ſtay the fountaine of originall ſinne, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Spirit of God: for as Chriſt had power to heale the woman of the bloody iſſue, which all the Phyſitians could not cure; ſo hath the holy Ghoſt, and no other, this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:959:6"/> power, priuiledge. It is a worke, that requires an infinite workeman to perfect. Pray then with the Prophet;<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.11.</note> 
               <hi>Lord take not thy holy ſpirit from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For the third and laſt euill, which is affliction and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; the Apoſtle alſo giueth vs a helpe againſt it; and that is comprehended in the verſe read vnto you: which is; <hi>though afflictions be not ioyous, but grieuous for the preſent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>yet they ſhall turne to our good at the latter ende.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, for our better proceeding, wee may obſerue two things: The one is, an affirmed propoſition, <hi>We know that all things worke together for good:</hi> The other, to whom theſe contrary things doe worke for good; and they are deſcribed, firſt, by an effect, that <hi>they loue God:</hi> ſecondly, by an adiunct, that <hi>they are called:</hi> which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is cloſely argued, by the Author and chiefe efficient, God; by the maner or rule, <hi>according to his purpoſe.</hi> In the propoſition note theſe particulars. Firſt, things: ſecondly, that theſe things worke: thirdly, that they all worke: fourthly, that they all worke together: fifthly, that they all worke together for good: ſixthly, and that we know, &amp;c. This for the propoſition: the limitation of its obiect, or fruit of its operation followeth. But before we come to the ſeuerall doctrines this verſe affoordeth, wee will clearely and briefly open the meaning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We]</hi> That is, I <hi>Paul,</hi> and other grounded and ſtrong Chriſtians, men and women; as well of the Laity, as Preachers of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Know]</hi> Knowledge is tooke often in Scripture for faith, becauſe they are inſeparable companions.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>For how can they beleeue in him, of whom they haue not heard?</hi> And ſo it is taken where <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>I know my Redeemer liueth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 19.25. Ioh. 17.3.</note> that is, I beleeue: and, <hi>This is eternall life, to know thee;</hi> that is, to beleeue in <hi>God, and whom he hath ſent Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſo may it be vnderſtood here, <hi>We know,</hi> that is, <hi>we beleeue,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Againe, Knowledge is either Notionall, or experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:959:7"/> Notionall is the bare apprehenſion of the truth of an Art,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.11. 2. Pet. 2.21.</note> or rule in any ſcience: but experimentall knowledge is, when we haue ſeene and felt the truth of a thing, verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either in our ſelues,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.7.</note> or others. And ſo <hi>Adam,</hi> after hee had eaten of the prohibited fruit, did know the nature of it in the effects,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.13.</note> by his owne experience. So <hi>Manaſſeh knew God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> and ſo <hi>Paul, the power of the Word.</hi> And in this place it may be tooke for a knowledge of experience, and not notionall onely. So that the full ſenſe is this: <hi>Wee are aſſured by faith, that all ſhall worke for good; and wee know it too by experience in our ſelues.</hi> Onely marke this, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall knowledge looketh backward, faith for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; the one, which is faith, relieth on the truth of the promiſe to be; the other, that is, experimental knowledge, is grounded vpon the word and will of God accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all] All,</hi> is tooke for all kinds, and all of all kindes, that is, <hi>collectiuely;</hi> excluding not any thing; or, for of each thing ſome, that is to ſay, <hi>diſtributiuely;</hi> excluding ſome things. For example: The Phariſies did <hi>tithe all hearbes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 11.42. 1. Tim. 2.4.</note> that is, of all kinds of hearbs: <hi>God would haue all men to be ſaued, viz.</hi> of all ſexes; men, women: and of all callings; ſuperiours, inferiours: or of all nations; Iewes, Gentiles, Barbarians, Scythians: And in the largeſt ſenſe it may be tooke in this place. For the Apoſtle ſeemes to anſwere a ſecret obiection. Some might ſay, What? ſhall affliction worke for good? the anſwere is, Yes: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, good or bad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Things]</hi> Things is any thing; from God to the leaſt <hi>ens,</hi> entity and being: for ſinne it ſelfe is called a thing; as, <hi>Theſe things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> that is, <hi>theſe ſinnes, haſt thou done.</hi> So that by <hi>things</hi> here is meant, any thing that can be named or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note>
               <hi>Worke]</hi> To wit, Turne, or fall out in the end and euent, by Gods diſpoſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together]</hi> Not apart, or as they be ſimply to bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in themſelues: for ſeparate affliction from grace, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:959:7"/> Gods <hi>ouer-ruling and diſpoſing hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 50.20.</note> it cannot worke but for <hi>euill.</hi> As ſimple poyſon, by it ſelfe receiued, doth kill; but being mixed with other ingredients, cureth the ſicke patient: ſo doth ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For good]</hi> That is, for the good of grace here,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> and glory hereafter: For we exclude naturall and ciuill goodneſſe from this good, in this place mentioned: though in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect, they may haue their prize and praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To them that loue God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 11.1. Mat. 10.37.</note>] Loue is ſometimes put for all the duties of religion. But <hi>Paul</hi> doth mention it heere, before any other thing, for two reaſons. Firſt, becauſe <hi>without loue</hi> al our proceedings are vnacceptable to God:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1. &amp;c.</note> this is that ſpirituall ſalt, that ſeaſoneth all our actions. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.14.</note> in regard that we cannot ſuffer any affliction for any perſon or thing, if we doe not loue it, and affect him: therefore <hi>Iacob ſerued ſeuen yeeres for Rahel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29.20.</note> 
               <hi>and they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him but a few daies, becauſe he loued her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And are called]</hi> Calling is manifold, either from the ſubiect place; ſo God called his people out of Egypt: or by the inſtrumentall cauſes;<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.3.</note> ſo God <hi>calleth</hi> by his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, iudgements, word and actions: or to an office; ſo <hi>Iudas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, it is effectuall, or not effectuall,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>Many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> but not truly, ſauingly.</p>
            <p>Now a man is ſaid to be <hi>effectually called,</hi> in reſpect of the manner; ordinarily, or extraordinarily: ordinarily is,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.2.</note> by the Word and Spirit, co-operating in a mans conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: extraordinarily, when the Spirit immediately, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Word read, or preached, ſpeaketh to the heart of a ſinner, ſaying; <hi>Ariſe, thou that art out of the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>turne into the right path, and walke on in the gate that leadeth to glory.</hi> And this effectuall calling, is that, that is here by the Apoſtle nominated; whether ordinarily, or extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily effected, that skils not; for ſo a thing bee well done, it matters not, whether it bee effected by a common, or more ſpeciall manner of proceeding; for that is not of the eſſence, but an adiunct to rhe thing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:959:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 8.5.</note>
               <hi>According]</hi> In this word is a ſimilitude of equall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To his]</hi> That is, <hi>Gods;</hi> they that referre it to man, are deceiued, and corrupt the Text: for God calleth not any for his foreſeene faith,<note place="margin">2. Tim 1 9.</note> or workes; but <hi>of his owne good pleaſure;</hi> and that, when man hath no purpoſe to bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Purpoſe]</hi> This word ſeemes to haue in it two things: the one, a rule by which a thing is done; the other, a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led reſolution to doe according to that rule: the firſt hath relation to the vnderſtanding; the ſecond, to the will; and we aſcribe both to God. For hee effecteth nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge, and all acts proceed from the will; the one guiding, and the other working, perfecting. Now both theſe, without offence to his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> may be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto him.</p>
            <p>And now will you heere the Metaphraſe in order, as it is ſummarily in the verſe contained? then thus it is, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, plainly: as if the Apoſtle had thus more amply reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, related:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot denie, but that afflictions and perſecutions are troubleſome, and not eaſily vndergone by them that either preach, or profeſſe the Goſpell; yet notwithſtanding, this may be a meanes to ſtrengthen the weake and feeble mindes of the faithfull; for we that are the Diſciples of Chriſt, doe know by experience, in reſpect of times paſt, and are by faith aſſured for the future daies; that, there is nothing whatſoeuer, as ſinne, ſorrow, death, or what can be named, or conceiued; but, to thoſe that loue the Lord, and are effectually called of his good pleaſure, it ſhall, in the euent and finall concluſion, by his wiſe diſpoſing, turne for the bringing of them to the truth of grace here, and the eternall perfection of glory hereafter.</hi> And this I conceiue to be the very true and naturall ſenſe of the verſe wee haue in hand: ſo let vs now proceed to gather ſome particular Doctrines, for our better and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction: and this I take to bee one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, that</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:959:8"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>All things worke together for good, vnto the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in another place hath a ſpeech ſomething to the ſame purpoſe;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Bodily exerciſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>profiteth a very little, yet godlineſſe is profitable for all things.</hi> But for the better proſecution of this point, we will make a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diſtribution. All things that are for our good, come either, firſt, from God; ſecondly, Satan; thirdly, others; fourthly and laſtly, from our ſelues: for in theſe wee may comprehend the moſt, if not all things, whereof wee haue to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> And concerning God, we will conſider, either his attributes, or his acts. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For his attributes, though they bee many, yet foure onely ſhall bee mentioned. And becauſe that Knowledge in God is moſt excellent (for Satan at the firſt vſed it as an argument to ſeduce our Parents,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall be as gods, knowing good and euill</hi>), we will declare how it worketh for the good of all his children.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by <hi>knowledge</hi> hee diſcerneth them from all repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated baſtards, and is able <hi>to call them by name.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33.12.</note> And is not this good for them? will it not comfort a child, in that his father knoweth him? By this hee alſo vnderſtandeth not onely who we be, but where we be, what we be, and the things that be the beſt for vs. Ignorance was a cauſe why <hi>Iſaac bleſſed Iacob in ſtead of Eſau;</hi> for had he knowne it,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 27.23.</note> he would not haue done it. Ignorance was the ground, why ſome of the <hi>Princes of this world put to death the Lord of life; for had they knowne him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>they would not haue crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13.</note> Ignorance cauſed <hi>Paul to perſecute the ſeruants of God;</hi> and many more euils haue ſprung from this blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Wherefore <hi>God, that knoweth his,</hi> cannot paſſe by them, and giue his bleſſings vnto others. So that <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in God is for his childrens good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not good vnto <hi>Hagar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 16. Matth. 2.</note> that the Lord knew her in the wilderneſſe? for <hi>Ieſus,</hi> when he was in Egypt? for <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſeeing the vprightneſſe of his heart? and for <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, <hi>The Lord knoweth whether I loue you, or not?</hi> yea,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.11.</note> by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:959:9"/> this all-ſufficient and ſeeing eye, he can collect the Elect from the foure ends of the world; ſingle them out of the deformed multitude; <hi>gather together their very bones; num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their haires;</hi> make a re-union of the ſame ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; conuent them at the laſt day before him; and <hi>reward them according to their workes.</hi> Nay, the <hi>diſcerning of our thoughts</hi> is profitable for the elect, for thereby they ſhall not be hindred, but helped. And by his <hi>Omniſcience</hi> hee diſcouereth the plots of the wicked, and knoweth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, how to fruſtrate and confound their cloſe and cunning enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>The ſicke patient is comforted, when as the Phiſitian vnderſtandeth the nature and danger of his diſeaſe, and the beſt way and meanes that can cure him. It cannot but be a vexation of ſpirit to be in calamitie, and his beſt friends ignorant of his perplexitie: Hence haue theſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull ſpeeches ſprung; <hi>Little doth my father and friends vnderſtand where I am, and my wofull condition: would to God they did: for then they would vſe meanes to free mee, comfort me.</hi> Wherefore when men are impriſoned vnder the Turke, or any Enemie; the firſt thing they doe, is to let their friends by letters, or other waies, to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it. Truly Gods knowledge is the very firſt ground of comfort to all the faithfull; for it maketh way, that euill may be remoued from them, and all that is good conferred vpon them; and the more wee thinke vpon Gods Omniſcience, the more will it yeeld vs matter of mirth and great reioycing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he would encourage his ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſerue God,<note place="margin">1. Chron. 28.9.</note> vſeth it for a ſtrong inducement: <hi>for the Lord knoweth all hearts.</hi> Chriſt pricketh his people for to pray on the ſame ground;<note place="margin">Matth 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Your heauenly Father knoweth the things whereof ye ſtand in need. Paul</hi> thereby ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth the feeble minded, in the apoſtacy of ſuch as had made great profeſſion;<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and others, perſwadeth the children of God, to doe good and ſuffer affliction, producing it as a reaſon: <hi>for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:959:9"/> eye of the Lord is ouer the righteous: He knoweth their works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.12. Reuel. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>and their dwelling place.</hi> So that we ſee, the Omniſcience of God in all reſpects may, and ſhall worke for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And from Gods Omniſcience wee will proceed to his Omnipotencie, and there wee ſhall perceiue, that it is alſo good for his children: for knowledge without power were to little purpoſe: but when theſe concurre in one perſon, what euill may not be preuented? what good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured? This power is of great force to confirme our faith; for by it we beleeue,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.3.</note> that he was able to create the world of nothing: that he doth, and can preſerue all things that they be not deſtroied,<note place="margin">Pſal. 114.5. &amp;c.</note> or the whole order thereof diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, ouerturned: that God can procure foode and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rather then we ſhould want, extraordinarily; that he can <hi>curbe</hi> and <hi>bridle</hi> the rage and violence of men and diuels; raiſe vp the dead; and <hi>make a new heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.39.40. &amp;c. Phil. 3.21. 2. Pet. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>and a new earth,</hi> wherein <hi>ſhall dwell righteouſneſſe.</hi> And what is it that he wanteth power to doe, if it may make for his glory, and our good? for <hi>The Lord is in heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.3.</note> 
               <hi>and doth whatſoeuer he will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.21.</note> it will confirme our confidence in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of all his promiſes, though they be neuer ſo many or great, or ſeeme ſometimes to exceede or croſſe nature. <hi>Dauid</hi> would <hi>not feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.1.</note> when <hi>the ſtrong hand of the Lord was with him. Abraham</hi> would willingly offer his ſonne; for <hi>God had power to raiſe him to life againe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.17.19.</note> In a word; <hi>if he be with vs,</hi> what mattereth it, <hi>Who,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> or what <hi>is againſt vs?</hi> For by his <hi>Power</hi> he is able to preſerue our eſſence from periſhing; and to keepe and ſupport vs, as a <hi>hand of ſtrength</hi> for euer: Thus you may perceiue, that his power is good for his children.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Now from his <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> let vs deſcend to his <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 73.1. Lam. 3.22.</note> and is not that the ſpring that comforteth the thirſtie ſoule? the fountaine of all ioy in miſerie? and that, that muſt ſupport vs from horrour and deſpaire? This will make vs willing to come before him in life, bold in death,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:959:10"/> and full of ioy in the great day of his comming, and our appearing. Yea, it will worke in vs compaſſion to our brethren,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.1.</note> 
               <hi>thankefulneſſe for his benefits;</hi> and will not <hi>his bountifulneſſe</hi> allure a good heart to <hi>true repentance?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.5.</note> But no man maketh doubt of this; therefore the more briefly we will touch it, and goe to the Attribute of his <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Iuſtice is a terrour to all wicked and vngodly men, they cannot endure to heare it; (but what will theſe perſons doe, when they muſt vndergoe it?) they checke him that will preach it, vrge it; crying, as the people in times paſt, <hi>Ye take too much vpon you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16.3. 1. Iohn 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>for all the Congregation is holy:</hi> yet is it <hi>exceeding comfortable</hi> and profitable to them that are effectually called, howeuer it worke with the wicked: for it wil moue them to ceaſe from ſinne, encourage them to doe good,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.4.5.6.</note> ſtrengthen them in faith, and worke in them patience, being by the prophane perſecuted: for they know,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.11.</note> that ſinne muſt not goe vnpuniſhed, godlineſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded, and that there <hi>is no reſpect of perſons with the Lord.</hi> In concluſion, it will make them carefull how to iudge the Lords proceedings,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.14.</note> not to accuſe him as <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 36.7.</note> to deny their owne merits, tremble at his word, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his extraordinary acts of prouidence,<note place="margin">Acts 16.30.</note> and to ſeeke for a righteouſneſſe, to ſatisfie the iuſtice of his Law. And thus could I touch the reſt of Gods Attributes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that as they are good in God, ſo to his children: But I omit them; and becauſe this, of all other things, doth moſt deceiue many, I will a little further follow it.</p>
            <p>We are to know, that the mercy and iuſtice of God are equall, as they be in him, and ſo be all his attributes; for whatſoeuer is in God, is God; and there is no difference betweene the eſſence and attributes of God, but in our apprehenſion: yet though they be equall amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, it may be demanded.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Whither is the greater in reſpect of the externall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, about which they are exerciſed?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> If we reſpect the latitude, the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſeemes to exceede his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and enlarge it ſelfe beyond it: for how many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:959:10"/> haue not the meanes of mercy, the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt?</hi> More want it, then they that enioy it. Againe,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> of the foure kinds of <hi>grounds,</hi> one but receiued <hi>the good ſeed,</hi> which is meant of them that are in the <hi>Church</hi> viſible. And Chriſt ſaith, that <hi>the way to heauen is narrow, and few find it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>but to hell broad, and many goe in thereat.</hi> Yet to ſpeake, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the truth is; if we regard the profunditie or depth of his <hi>mercy,</hi> then in that it hath the preheminence; and in foure things it will appeare: firſt, the Lord found out a way to ſaue man,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15. 1. Pet. 1.12.</note> when <hi>Satan</hi> or the <hi>good Angels could not peepe into that ſecret.</hi> It went beyond the Serpents skill for all his ſubtilty, how a finite creature could make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſatisfaction. Secondly,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.16.</note> in that <hi>God gaue his owne onely Sonne</hi> freely to take vpon him mans nature, that there might be a reconciliation. Thirdly, that he was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receiue the debt from a ſuertie, and not at the <hi>deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> hands, for it was in his owne election and libertie.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.9. &amp;c.</note> Fourthly, and herein is his mercy manifeſted wonderfully, that he hath ſent his Word and <hi>Spirit to beare witneſſe of</hi> this great worke to open mens blind eies,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.16.</note> that they might ſee into it; infuſe faith into their vnbeleeuing hearts to credit it, and in particular to apply it: ſo that in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, they that vnderſtand it, and are aſſured that they be partakers of this <hi>rich mercy,</hi> may ſay, that <hi>it is a depth paſt finding out.</hi> But firſt get vnder the act of his mercie,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> taſte of it, and then maiſt thou iuſtly, and with comfort commend it; otherwiſe, be it, as it is, infinite, it will profit thee nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And now we will come to ſpeake briefly of ſome acts or effects that proceed from God, and declare how they alſo doe worke for his childrens good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, his <hi>Decree</hi> is profitable for them; for though it exclude the reprobate from all true bleſſedneſſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.24.</note> yet it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the Elect within the booke of life and ſaluation. The Apoſtle compares it to a <hi>foundation,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.19. And ſo it is in three reſpects: Firſt, becauſe it comes from God, who is the originall and beginner of all things. Secondly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:959:11"/> in regard that it is the <hi>baſis</hi> and ground, on which all the worke of mans ſaluation ſtands. And thirdly, in reſpect of the firmeneſſe and ſureneſſe of it; for it abideth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and ſtedfaſt for euer: ſo that he who is builded vpon this rocke (as all the faithfull be), cannot fall from the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of perfect bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, the worke of creation, and mans generation is good for his people; for that is the beginning of their actuall well-being, and a ſtep to bleſſing; howbeit, it had been good for <hi>Iudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.24.</note> and the vnbeleeuers, <hi>they had neuer been borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And mans effectual <hi>Vocation</hi> is good too, whether it be ſooner or latter: if the Lord call a man in his youth, why, is not this a rare priuiledge? and ſhall he not be better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to reſiſt all euill in the time of age? Suppoſe the Lord ſingle a man out in his more ancient yeeres, yet it ſhall bee good for him alſo: for hee ſhall diſcerne more clearely, and that with admiration, the <hi>patience and long ſuffering of the Lord;</hi> perceiue his power the more, in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him from that long, and ſtrong habit of wickednes: he will make the more haſte to heauen, as the ſhaft to the marke that hath been long held in the bowe; worke the more willingly in the <hi>Lords vineyard</hi> ſo ſhort a time; and he thereby will be the more hopefull of old ſinners, leſſe proane finally to cenſure any. And is not this alſo <hi>good</hi> for him?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Beſides, let one depth of afflictions, like the waues of water, ſlow after another; yet ſhall they leade him from ſinne, and draw him more cloſe to the Law of God, make him more pitifull to his ſick brother, and weane him from the loue of this world, exerciſe all grace in him to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, and ſeale to his ſoule the more certaintie of his ſaluation.<note place="margin">2. King. 22.20.</note> What if death deſtroy his daies in youth? is <hi>he not tooke from the euill to come?</hi> and ſhall not a well-led life yeeld comfort at the day of death? doth he not the ſooner take poſſeſſion of his fathers inheritance, and <hi>reſt from his labours?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 14.13.</note> yea, and is not then the day of a good
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:959:11"/> mans death, better then the day of his birth?</p>
            <p>And if his life and daies be prolonged; why?<note place="margin">Prou. 16 31.</note> is not <hi>gray haires a crowne of glorie, being found in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Now from God, and his acts, come wee to <hi>Satan;</hi> and wee ſhall eaſily diſcerne, that his plots and malice ſhall worke for good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> He cauſed man to fall from his integritie at the firſt; but what loſt he? firſt, is he not a member now of a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious head, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Lord? Secondly, is not his ſtanding more certaine, and he not ſubiect to change, and fall for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? and this is the reaſon why <hi>Adam</hi> had a Sacrament in the <hi>Garden,</hi> of good and euill, to ſeale life or death; but we in <hi>Chriſt</hi> haue none, but ſuch as ſeale vp our ſaluation. Thirdly, ſhall not our eſtate be more glorious, in reſpect of the place of our habitation? For if <hi>Adam</hi> had ſtood (probably as ſome thinke), we had neuer been tranſlated from earth to heauen: for euery creature (ſay they) was to be bleſſed in that ſtate and place, where the Lord at the firſt put them; as Angels in heauen, Fiſhes in the ſea; and conſequently, Man and Beaſt on the earth: and our aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion comes by Chriſt; for from the Deitie, hauing more power to carry the humanitie to heauen, then the humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie any waies to moue the Deitie, ſprings our ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to confirme this <hi>propoſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.47.</note> when he ſaith; that <hi>The firſt man was of the earth, earthly; the ſecond from heauen, heauenly:</hi> endeauouring not only to proue the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> but the aſcenſion of the body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by the merits of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> So that Satan did not hurt, but helpe vs, though not willingly; yet through the mercy of God, on his part freely; but on Satans by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And what though he tempt vs ſtill? why, we may learne wiſdome of him; as for to get power againſt the day of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; and it will aſſure a man that he is Chriſts ſheepe, and in the path to heauen, when hee finds Satan ſo to tempt him, and reſiſt him: for thus he diſputeth; If I were not at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:959:12"/> liberty, why ſhould the diuell thus trouble me, tempt me? <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, that he learned much good (meaning in theſe former reſpects) from the aduerſary of mankind; though the Papiſts, blind guides, ſcandalize him for it, and accuſe him to haue been familiar with the diuell. And no doubt, but as a man learnes wit by going to Law with a cunning aduerſarie; ſo the ſonnes of God in our daies haue good by his tentations, in finding out his depths, and feeling Gods ſtrong arme to plucke them out of his mouth: and he that neuer learned wiſdome from Satan (though he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to teach him any), may be iuſtly ſuſpected, not to be in the way to heauen, 2. Cor. 2.11.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thus from him, let vs ſtep to mankind, the which bee our brethren in the fleſh, or ſpirit; and we will begin with the wicked ones.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> What if the <hi>Canaanites</hi> be ſtill among the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> is it not good for them? for firſt, if the ſonne runne from his father, why let him fall into the hand of an vncircumciſed <hi>Philistim,</hi> he will whip him home againe. Secondly, the prouidence of God ouer his, will the more appeare in their preſeruation. Thirdly, it will make the faithfull to looke better to their footing, that they haue not cauſe to blaſpheme the name of the Lord, or ſpeake euill of his lawes: wee ſee <hi>Lot</hi> liued better in <hi>Sodom</hi> amongſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then when hee came to <hi>Zoar</hi> from out of them. Fourthly, they preuent much ſinne, that the righteous are ſubiect vnto: for ſuppoſe that a man would wrong the <hi>King</hi> of his impoſt and cuſtome; ſell away (as wee haue heard ſome doe) their powder, ſhot, and the like prouiſion: why, an honeſt man cannot, if hee would haue way for the wicked; for they lie at euery aduantage; and, like dogs, deuoure that carrion, that might choake and poiſon the godly. And doe we not ſee, that a flower growing amongſt Onyons and Garlicke is ſweeter, then if it were among more pleaſant herbes? for the ſower roote ſuckes the bad iuice, and leaues the better for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:959:12"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And it is out of all queſtion, that one good man hath benefit by another: For firſt, they are partakers of one anothers prayers; and is not this a good thing? Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they haue a fellow-feeling of one anothers miſeries; and is not this to be eaſed of part of their burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they will comfort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they be feeble minded, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue them in neceſſity: and what better for ſuch as bee in that condition? Fourthly, they all concurre, to make vp one compleat and perfect Temple, for Gods Spirit to dwell in; and by this relation, haue they not good, one by, and from another? what if they iarre now and then, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> were ſometimes ſtirred amongſt themſelues? yet ſhall not the falling out of friends, bee a meanes to renew more firmely their former affection; like a bone, being knit, that hath been broken, is the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer afterwards? yea, ſuch ſhall be reconciled in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for we reade,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.11.</note> that <hi>Paul</hi> willed <hi>Timothy</hi> to bring <hi>Marke with him; for he was profitable to miniſter.</hi> A rare ſpirit was this in <hi>Paul,</hi> and hard to bee found in theſe dayes; that would ſend from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Troas</hi> for an aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Finally, let vs now come to our ſelues; and if wee bee effectually called, all that is within vs, or that proceedeth from vs, ſhall turne to our benefit: not onely the good graces of Gods ſpirit, and all outward fauours, with our holy actions; but our Originall ſinne and actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. For firſt, this inbred corruption will humble vs to the earth, and make vs <hi>vile in our owne eyes.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe vs to pray earneſtly and often: and thirdly, will we, nill we, to denie our owne power and free-will: and fourthly, to ſeeke to God for mercy in Chriſt his Sonne. And our actuall ſinnes will worke the ſame effects alſo: And is not he that is burthened, wounded, humbled; in the way to be eaſed, healed, exalted?</p>
            <p>I could inſtance in particulars: <hi>Sampſon</hi> (ſome thinke) ſinned in matching with the Philiſtim;<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.</note> yet thereby God brought a great deſtruction vpon the Churches enemies;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:959:13"/> and made him a liuely type of our Lord. <hi>Iſaac</hi> miſt it, through circumſtance,<note place="margin">Gen. 26.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>inſporting with Rebeccah;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it was a meanes of his ſafe deliuery out of the Kings hands. <hi>Iacob</hi> may ſteale <hi>his brothers</hi> bleſſing, but cannot the Lord ſanctifie it vnto him?<note place="margin">1. Sam. 21. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids faining of himſelfe madde,</hi> cannot well bee excuſed; what of that? God can ſo worke, that thereby he ſhall eſcape death and danger. And let this be obſerued: that as a man hauing tumbled in the mire and mudde, by occaſion whereof waſheth off his clothes many leſſer ſpots, then which hee before that fall neglected: ſo the faithfull, through the commiſſion of ſome great and fowle offence, be brought by repentance to cleanſe themſelues of ſmaller ſinnes, then which had not yet been reformed, except the other had befallen them. And theſe may ſerue to manifeſt the truth of the thing: that <hi>actuall ſinne</hi> ſhall, as it hath, <hi>worke,</hi> by the good hand of <hi>God,</hi> for his childrens benefit, and great commodity. And now I come to render ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſons of the generall <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> And firſt of all, who can hinder the Lord from this action?<note place="margin">Prou. 21.30.</note> Is there any <hi>wiſedome, counſell, or vnderſtanding againſt him?</hi> cannot he tell that made all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, brought light out of darkneſſe, how to turne all for the good of the godly? Who, or what is able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it? no policy or inuention of man or Angell.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Againe, his power is proportionable to his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>for as he is wiſe in heart, ſo is hee mighty in ſtrength.</hi> He can confound the policy of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> breake the arme of Satan, and turne the fierie bullets of his foes, bark into their faces, to fight for him and his, and deſtroy the aduerſaries; he can cauſe all the crooked wheeles of the wicked to runne ſtraight, for the execution of his good pleaſure. This he hath done; and this he can, and will ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Moreouer, as he knoweth how to doe it, and hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to effect it: ſo hath he a will to execute it: <hi>and who is able to hinder</hi> that irreſiſtable motion?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 9.19.22.</note> will chaffe, caſt on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:959:13"/> the violent ſtreame, ſtay the current thereof from running? ſhall a feather hinder the turbulent wind from blowing? or the piſmire moue the earth out of the worlds center? why then, may his will be preuented, fruſtrated?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> And is it not for his owne glory, to effect this for the ſeed of the woman, and for the ſhame of the wicked, to bruiſe the head of that ſubtill Serpent? Yes doubtleſſe: for if all his plots were not ouerthrowne, then Satan and his brood ſhould haue ſomewhat to glory in, God to bee humbled for; but they ſhall neuer effect their willes; or the Lord be preuented of his.<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>They may weaue the webbe of the Spider;</hi> but a winde ſhall huffe it away: <hi>ſit, and hatch the Cockatrice egges;</hi> but <hi>they ſhall breake forth into a Serpent,</hi> that ſhall eate out her owne and their bowels. And thus we come to make vſe of the doctrine, which is profitable euery manner of way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, for confutation of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who maintaine, that, <hi>A man effectually called, iuſtified, and, in ſome meaſure ſanctified, may fall totally and for euer.</hi> If the Popes poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be a truth, then the Apoſtles is a falſhood; for if one may fall from ſauing grace, and vtterly periſh, how can all things be ſaid to <hi>worke together for good</hi> to ſuch a perſon? And in my opinion, no one Text (though there bee many for that purpoſe) doth more make againſt our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then this we haue in hand. And what a comfortleſſe doctrine is that, which they defend.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The next is for <hi>reprehenſion</hi> of thoſe which ſay, It is in vaine to be religious;<note place="margin">Iob 21.15.</note> 
               <hi>What profit is there in ſeruing the Almighty?</hi> What profit? why all profit: for <hi>all things ſhall worke together for their good, ſinne, Satan, death, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hell.</hi> Yea, the worſt thing that befalleth any of his children, ſhall doe them more good, then the beſt ſhall, that can befall the wicked.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.26.</note> 
               <hi>It was better for Moſes to ſuffer affliction with the faithfull, then to haue been called the ſonne of Pharaohs daughter, and enioyed the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon.</hi> Oh that the men of our age did conſider but this one thing! then doubtleſſe they would alter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:959:14"/> their minds, and ſpeedily change their manners. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall into vtter deſolation, becauſe they doe not deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ponder this in their hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> And here it may teach the enemies of Gods children to learne a point of wiſedome; and (if they will not ſhew themſelues mad men) to amend.<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2. Pſal. 11.2.</note> The <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and <hi>Atheist</hi> may <hi>band themſelues againſt the Lords annointed; ſhoot at the vpright in heart;</hi> and <hi>make haſt to the ſpoyle.</hi> But <hi>the righteous God ſhall cut their cords aſunder. Why then doe the Heathen rage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the people murmure a vaine thing? O yee fooles, when will ye be wiſe?</hi> I haue often wondred, why they ſtill perſeuere in their miſchiefe: But either they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not the truth;<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> for <hi>the foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God:</hi> or elſe with ſome of the former <hi>Phariſies,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> they <hi>haue ſinned vnto death,</hi> and that is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe implacable: and if not ſo; yet like <hi>Elymas the Sorcerer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.3. and 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>they are full of the diuell,</hi> and purſue them of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, or for lucre's ſake; and haue their hearts ſo ſet vpon malice,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.32.</note> that though they are conuinced in iudgement, and know that they doe euill, and that <hi>God</hi> will reuenge; yet will they perſiſt in their wicked practiſes. Doe wee not ſee ſome wrangling Clyants, that though their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſell tell them that their caſe is naught, and will not beare an action: yet they will to Law notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and miſpend their time, and waſte their wealth? e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo Satans inſtruments will purſue of enuie, although they labour in vaine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> And this doctrine may teach vs many profitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we learne, that <hi>There is a particular prouidence</hi> of God in all things: for if not, how ſhould affliction, ſinne and euill worke for good? were it not a matter impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? ſome haue dreamed of <hi>fortune</hi> and <hi>chance;</hi> others conceited, that the inferiour creatures and their actions haue been gouerned by a generall courſe of Nature, to produce their effects; and that the Lord doth not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly guide and rule them. But by this point wee ſee,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:959:14"/> that they are all groſly deluded, deceiued.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we may gather hence, that <hi>There is but one chiefe Monarchie nor gouernment in the world;</hi> becauſe all things worke for that one end, to expreſſe that one ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power; for if there were more gouernours, then it could not be thus, therefore there is but one Monarchy, the moſt excellent gouernment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly we hence may collect, that, <hi>In what condition ſoeuer a good man is, he is neuer miſerable;</hi> for be it what it will, all is ſtill in working for his preſent and future good.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that ſome good may bee drawne out of the worſt thing; elſe all things could not turne and fall out for the profit of the Lords choſen.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, againe, hence wee may learne how to direct our prayers; to aske outward and ſome inward fauours conditionally: for <hi>pouerty, ſickneſſe, bondage and terrour,</hi> may (by the ouer and al-ruling hand of God, bee as good for vs as <hi>proſperity, health, peace,</hi> and <hi>freedome.</hi> Therefore let vs pray with our Lord and Maſter, <hi>O Father, not mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> 
               <hi>but thy will be done: Doe with me as ſeemeth beſt in thine eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, let vs, ſeeing this is ſo, neuer except againſt the Lords manner of proceedings; wee cannot teach him wiſedome;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>for the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then the wiſedome of man:</hi> let the Lord vſe what inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he will: for <hi>clay and ſpittle, Diotrephes and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,</hi> will ſerue his turne well enough, and fit his purpoſe. If thy brethren ſell thee; thy wife betray thee; or thy familiar friend <hi>lift vp his heele againſt thee:</hi> yet <hi>fret not,</hi> complaine not, but patiently expect the euent rather. And this is the principall dutie of euery <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> dwell where God would haue thee; doe what hee commands thee; and waſh in that water he directs thee; for this is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Saints. Let <hi>Shimei</hi> curſe thee; <hi>Alexander</hi> reſiſt thee; or an incarnate <hi>Diuell</hi> purſue thee; ſtill lay <hi>thy hand vpon thy mouth,</hi> and with <hi>Iob</hi> ſay, Why,<note place="margin">Iob 23.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>God is in one mind, and who can turne him? hee will bring to paſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:959:15"/> the thing hee hath decreed of mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> Another generall vſe may ſerue for <hi>conſolation.</hi> Doe but meditate of this poynt, ponder it well in thy mind; and it will be a notable ſtay to ſupport thy feeble and fainting ſpirit. Are thy croſſes great and many? haſt thou a long time beene exerciſed by them? what then? <hi>all this is for thy good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16.</note> He that <hi>beleeues</hi> this, <hi>will not,</hi> cannot <hi>make haſt.</hi> Some mourne that they were conuerted no ſooner; grieue, that they can finde comfort no ſpeedier; ſigh, that they can pray no better; droupe, that they are exalted no higher; and are tormented in heart, that they ſee not things in Church and Common-wealth in a more ſpeciall manner to proſper: yet, though in ſome reſpects this may be tolerable, they may miſſe it in the extreame.</p>
            <p>This vſe is worthy to be engrauen with a pen of iron in ſtone; written with the point of a Diamond in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of thy heart; for, next <hi>faith in Chriſt,</hi> it is the chiefe ground of all comfort here, and full felicity hereafter. Yea doubtleſſe, this is an herbe, though one in number, yet, if thou be Gods, it will heale all thy diſeaſes, bee they innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable; if ſo be thou remember it; and, in the time of need, by faith truly apply it. Wherefore let this point ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſlip out of thy mind.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>6</label> Finally, if all <hi>worke for good,</hi> how ſhould we be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, that haue begun well, to goe on; and thoſe that haue not, now to begin? Haſt thou liued a long time leaudly? followed the faſhions of this euill world? obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in the very luſts of it? been ruled by the <hi>Prince that reigneth in the children of diſobedience;</hi> and <hi>giuen vp thy members, as ſo many ſeruants to worke all wickedneſſe and vncleanneſſe?</hi> liuing in knowne ſinnes, whereof thy conſcience hath conuicted thee, and the Miniſter repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thee? Yet now turne vnto God; repent for thy ſinnes paſt, and amend; and <hi>all ſhall worke for thy good.</hi> Truly if men did giue credit to this, they could not but (I am ſure they ought to) amend.</p>
            <p>Who would not be willing to goe ſuch a iourney or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:959:15"/> voyage, when as euery looke of the eye, motion of the hand, ſtep with the foot, and word in the way ſhould worke for good, and produce it profitable effect? Nay, when euery fall, wind, ſtorme, or hurt, ſhould bring great aduantage vnto the paſſenger? and this is the gaine of godlineſſe: and thus ſhall he bee rewarded that will tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to heauen. Wouldeſt thou then be wiſe? then know God, and ſerue him. Wouldeſt thou grow in wealth? why, ſet vpon all good actions. What if thou be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of that end thou aimeſt at, and is firſt in thy intention? yet, how euer it fall out, the euent ſhall be good.</p>
            <p>Who would not plant ſuch trees in his Orchard, that will neuer be barren? ſowe ſuch ſeed in his cloſe, whereof not one corne ſhall miſcarry? and be maſter of ſuch a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in the which euery action would bring profit, great commoditie? Why, Godlineſſe is ſuch a tree, ſuch a graine, and ſuch a calling:<note place="margin">Prou. 3.17.</note> for <hi>all her waies are waies of pleaſure, and all her paths proſperity.</hi> If this then will not moue thee to <hi>ceaſe from euil, and learne to do good:</hi> I can ſay no more vnto thee, <hi>But the good Lord haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee haue heard the proofe and manifold vſe of the point; yet becauſe wicked men are prone to draw the worſt concluſions out of the beſt propoſitions; a caution (and that not amiſſe) may be added to the doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doe not <hi>ſinne becauſe grace doth abound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caution.</note> and in regard <hi>all things</hi> may <hi>worke for</hi> thy <hi>good;</hi> ſay not (as ſome haue from this very ground) <hi>Let vs do euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.8, Iude 4. Rom. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>that good may come thereof:</hi> for this is, to <hi>turne the grace of God into wantonnes,</hi> that ſhould <hi>leade thee to</hi> true <hi>repentance,</hi> and the way, not to <hi>worke out thy ſaluation,</hi> but thy condemnation. Nay, let vs the rather by all meanes ſeeke, and turne all things to his glory, that bringeth ſo ſtrange and wonderfull things to paſſe, for our good. I cannot tell what men will doe; but I am ſure I know what they ought, and that from this conſideration.</p>
            <p>And now, out of many, I wil briefly collect and handle one other doctrine that my text affoords me, which is, that</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:959:16"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>All things worke together for good, but to ſuch as are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led effectually of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This propoſition, I told you at firſt, had a limitation; for <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>we know</hi> that all things worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the good of all men; but for ſuch <hi>as loue God, and are called according to the purpoſe of God:</hi> ſo that a man cannot be aſſured of the one, vntill he can proue himſelfe to be of that number, and to haue the ſame things, that be in, and of the other. And theſe people, of whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh, were <hi>the called of God,</hi> Rom. 1.6. and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe they that are called are elected; for God doth not effectually call any, whom hee hath not loued and choſen from eternity. Now this is the beginning of all bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Againe, if they be effectually called, then are they iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, made <hi>coheires with Chriſt,</hi> and ſhall aſſuredly bee ſaued: for if they haue the firſt, ſecond and third linke of the chaine; they muſt needs haue the other, and the end alſo. And the Apoſtle himſelfe, it ſeemes, giues the ſame reaſon of the doctrine, in the verſes following. Now the maine vſe of the point is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Let vs hence learne, <hi>to make our calling ſure,</hi> otherwiſe we cannot haue any true ground of our <hi>Election,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> or <hi>iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and conſequently, that any thing <hi>ſhall worke</hi> for our good, and glorification. For hee that is not called of God, though he may be in Gods decree, yet he is not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally iuſtified; therefore can neuer, vntill that bee effected, make any comfortable vſe of the doctrine. And for the true triall hereof, let theſe <hi>ſignes</hi> following be marked.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of all, what power haſt thou felt in the voice of the word preached? how hath it knocked at the doore, and ſounded in the eare of thy ſoule? what hath the Lord ſaid vnto thee? doeſt thou remember? Thou art to know, that the word of God is liuely, <hi>and mighty in operation,</hi> when it worketh ſauingly in the ſoules of the hearers: it openeth the eare; ſmiteth and woundeth the ſpirit; pricketh and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:959:16"/> pierceth the heart, and maketh the face of man looke pale and wan. Hence it is compared <hi>to a hammer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note> that beateth to duſt and powder; <hi>a two-edged ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>that deuideth and cutteth aſunder the ioynts and the marrow;</hi> and to a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>fier,</hi> that burneth and waſteth vp all chaffe, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter combuſtible; yea, that will either change, or make the very ſtones to flie in pieces. Why then, hath this Word broken thy hard and flinty heart? made a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thee and thy ſinne? and cauſed thy zeale to burne within thee, and like a flame of fier to proceede out from thee? then it worketh naturally, and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, How haſt thou anſwered the Lord, when hee hath called vpon thee? What did hee command thee? and haſt thou done it? If God call by his effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall voyce, hee will cauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> a King to replie;<note place="margin">Pſalm. 27.8.</note> 
               <hi>Lord I will ſeeke thy face: Moſes</hi> to anſwere at the laſt; <hi>I will goe whither thou wilt: Paul</hi> to crie out;<note place="margin">Acts 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>Who art thou that I perſecute?</hi> and the ſtouteſt heart, and moſt obſtinate perſon, with the <hi>Iaylor,</hi> to fall at a poore Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters feete, and burſt foorth; <hi>Sir,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 16.30.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall I doe to bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> Well: ſearch now thine owne ſoule; conſider with thy ſelfe what the Lord ſpake, and thou haſt done. Hee hath called vpon thee to be <hi>ſober,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.13. Luke 6.35.</note> and thou followeſt <hi>drunkenneſſe;</hi> to be liberall, and <hi>lend freely,</hi> and thou art become a biting and liuing <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>to flee ſinne</hi> aboue <hi>all things,</hi> and thou daily runneſt after it. Is this to heare the Lords voice? and to be effectually called? No, no. But if thou repent that thou haſt gone aſtray, ſmite thy hand vpon thy breaſt, reſolueſt hence-forward to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his Word, and crieſt out, and often,<note place="margin">Luke 18.13.</note> 
               <hi>Good Lord bee mercifull to mee a ſinner;</hi> then <hi>bee of good comfort, thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee: for God hath effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third place; What loue haſt thou to that Word, by which thou haſt been called? How art thou affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with it? and of what price doeſt thou value it?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:959:17"/> Canſt thou ſay with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 23.12.</note> 
               <hi>I reſpect it aboue my daily and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed food?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15.16. Pſalm. 19.10.</note> with <hi>Ieremiah, It is the reioycing of my ſoule?</hi> with <hi>Dauid, It is ſweeter to me, then the hony-combe?</hi> In a word, doeſt thou <hi>loue it aboue much fine gold? meditate in it day and night?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>delight to heare it?</hi> and, with the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, <hi>receiue it with great ioy in affliction?</hi> Why, no man dares deny, but that thou art ſingled out of the world, and <hi>brought into the liberty of Gods children:</hi> but if thou ſtop the eare at the Word, ſcoffe at the Word, and ſpit, and ſpue it out of thy mouth; thou art yet dead, and God by his voice hath not truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And in concluſion: What diſpoſition doeſt thou find to call others, as thou art called? How art thou affected to call home labourers into the Lords harueſt? Sure hee that is called, will call others, and that foure waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, he wil cal vpon them to heare the word: for thinks hee, the Lord may call them, as hee hath done me. Thus did the poore <hi>woman of Samaria,</hi> running home, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her neighbours;<note place="margin">Iohn 4.29.</note> 
               <hi>Come, ſee a man, that hath told me all that euer I did.</hi> And a good heart, when he heares the voyce of God powerfull in the Miniſter; Oh, thinkes hee, that ſuch and ſuch were here now! it might pleaſe the Lord to call them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they will call others by exhortation and inſtruction,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>prouing if God at any time will giue them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that they may come to amendment of life, out of the ſnares of the diuell.</hi> Thus did that good man call; <hi>Come vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 66.16.</note> 
               <hi>and I will tell you, what the Lord hath done for my ſoule: I will teach you the feare of the Lord.</hi> Pſalm. 34.11.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, beſides, they will ſeek to allure others into the way by a good and holy example; and (if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.1. 1. Pet. 3.1.</note> to win thoſe thereby, that are without the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when all this will not preuaile, then they will giue themſelues to prayer; the Father for his ſonne: <hi>God
<pb facs="tcp:959:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſwade Iapheth to dwell in the tents of Shem: Steuen,</hi> for his enemies: <hi>Lord lay not this ſinne to their charge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.60. Luk. 23.34.</note> And our Lord, for his crucifiers; <hi>Father, forgiue them, for they know not what they doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mayeſt thou try thy ſelfe, whether thou be called of God, or not: If theſe things bee in thee thou art; and <hi>all things ſhall worke together for thy good:</hi> but if not, thou art not called; and as yet, all things are working together for thy euill. <hi>The Lord open thine eyes. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soliſapienti Deo gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
